Welcome back, everyone, to Walmart
Academy's The Art of Feedback. I’m Jamie,
alongside leadership expert Alex. In our
last episode, we talked all about the
timing of feedback—catching those
real-time moments. Today, we are tackling
the million-dollar question: How do we
actually say the words without it turning
into a defensive argument?
[sighs] It is the toughest part of the
job for so many leaders, Jamie. Because
feedback can easily get clouded by raw
emotion, or misinterpretation. If we
aren't careful, a well-intentioned
conversation can quickly go off the
rails. That is exactly why leaders have
to use a structured approach.
We... need a blueprint!
[energetic] Exactly! And the absolute
best blueprint out there is the SBI
feedback model. It is a simple, highly
effective framework designed to make
feedback significantly clearer. It keeps
the conversation strictly focused on
observable facts, rather than subjective
assumptions or emotions.
[Enthusiastic] Which naturally dials down
the defensiveness, I imagine?
Dramatically. [emphatic] By relying on
this strict structure, you reduce
misinterpretation, drop the defensive
shields, and pave the way for a
productive, growth-focused dialogue.
Okay, [surprised] I'm sold. What does SBI
stand for?
[thoughtful] It stands for Situation,
Behavior, and Impact. Let’s break them
down. First up is the "S"—Situation. You
must define the exact "where" and "when"
of the situation you are discussing. Be
specific.
So, what would be an ineffective way to
do that?
An ineffective start sounds like this:
[annoyed] "When dealing with customers,
you always act…" It's too broad, and
words like "always" immediately make
people defensive, because it feels like
an attack on their character.
[Enthusiastic] That makes sense. So, how
do we fix it using the "Situation" step?
You anchor it in time and space. An
effective example would be: [explaining]
"In our team meeting on Tuesday…" You've
just established the factual setting. No
one can argue with Tuesday's team
meeting.
[happy] Perfect. Okay, so we have our
Situation. What is the "B"—Behavior?
[Cheeky] This is where you must describe
the specific behavior that actually
occurred. Again, just the observable
facts. What did you see or hear?
So, avoiding things like [annoyed] "you
were being rude," which is an assumption,
and instead saying what they actually
did?
[energetic] Exactly! Examples of
observable behavior would be: crossing
arms, interrupting others, returning late
from lunch, or walking by a spill and not
taking action. You are simply stating the
action that took place within that
specific situation.
[clears throat] Alright, that brings us
to the final piece: the "I"—Impact.
[emphatic] Yes. You have to clearly
explain the impact that the behavior had
on you, the customer, or the business as
a whole. This is the "why it matters"
part of the conversation.
[curious] Can you give us an example of a
negative impact?
[thoughtful] Sure. Let's say the behavior
was leaving equipment out. The impact
statement would be: [serious] "When
ladders aren't secured, our customers are
put at risk." You connect the action
directly to the consequence.
And we talked last episode about how
important it is to reinforce positive
behavior, too. How does SBI work for
that?
[thoughtful] It works beautifully for
positive reinforcement! Let's say an
associate was doing a great job listening
during a huddle. Your impact statement
might be: "When you make space for others
to finish their thoughts, it helps them
feel heard and valued.".
[energetic] Situation, Behavior, Impact.
It takes the guesswork and the emotion
entirely out of the equation.
[chuckles] It does. It transforms a
stressful confrontation into a clear,
factual, and supportive conversation. Oh,
and Jamie? One more thing before we go.
[laughs nervously] Uh oh. I don't like
that tone.
[excited] Next up, it's test time. I
highly hope you—and everyone
listening—have been paying attention.
Wait, a pop quiz?! [Cheeky] Is this going
on my permanent record? I thought we were
friends!
[Cheeky] Consider this your "S"—the
Situation. Next episode, we're testing
your "B"—Behavior.
[laughs nervously] And the "I" is going
to be the Impact on my ego. [chuckles]
Alright, folks, grab your No. 2 pencils
and cram while you can.