Welcome back to Walmart Academy's The Art
of Feedback. In our last episode, we
talked about the psychology of
feedback—how that "personal lens" makes
us all react differently to the exact
same words. I'm Jamie, and I'm back with
our resident leadership strategist, Alex.
Hey, Jamie! Now that we know how feedback
is processed in the brain, it’s time to
talk about the when and the why. Today is
all about the chronology and purpose of
intervention.
"Intervention" sounds like a heavy word,
but we are really talking about the
timing of feedback, right? — Why is the
clock so critical here?
Because the effectiveness of feedback is
intrinsically linked to when you deliver
it. Timely feedback matters immensely
because it allows leaders to step in
while the moment is still highly
relevant. If you intervene in real-time,
learning can happen instantly. You can
clarify assumptions and offer support
right then and there.
So it’s not just about reacting faster
when things go wrong.
Exactly. The goal isn't merely to react
faster to issues; it's to intervene early
enough to actively shape outcomes, rather
than just measuring them after the fact.
That's a great distinction—shaping the
outcome versus measuring it later. So
what does that look like in practice?
It looks like capitalizing on.. everyday
moments. Leaders are presented with so
many chances every single day to check
in, share their observations, and guide
their associates. [short pause] When you
use those real-time moments, it creates a
workplace culture where feedback feels
completely normal. It becomes entirely
supportive and focused on continuous
growth, rather than being this
intimidating, sweat-inducing event saved
for a formal performance review. [exhales
sharply].
[big laugh] I know what you mean and in
those everyday, real-time moments, what
are we actually trying to achieve?
There are really just two primary
objectives for giving feedback. First, to
redirect behaviors that are starting to
drift away from established expectations.
[thoughtful] So, a gentle course
correction.
Right. [short pause] And second, to
reinforce the behaviors that are working
exceptionally well and driving success.
We have to cheerlead the good stuff, too!
[sighs] Which is so easy to forget when
we are busy putting out everyday fires.
We usually only think of feedback as
correcting mistakes.
[chuckles] Exactly, but positive
reinforcement is arguably just as
critical. It actually reminds me of a
foundational piece of advice from Sam
Walton. Mr. Sam always said:
[inspirational] "Appreciate everything
your associates do for the business.
Nothing else can quite substitute for a
few well-chosen, well-timed, sincere
words of praise. They're absolutely free
and worth a fortune.".
"Free and worth a fortune." [chuckles] I
love that so much. And I notice he
explicitly calls out that those words
need to be well-timed.
He hit the nail on the head. That goes
right back to our point about the
timeline. Timely, ongoing feedback acts
as a safeguard. It helps catch small dips
in performance early on to ensure
expectations and performance remain
perfectly aligned. If you intervene
early, the associate can adjust their
course while the issue is still
completely manageable.
[thoughtful] It prevents a molehill from
becoming a mountain. [short pause] Plus,
speaking from an associate's perspective,
consistent feedback builds immense trust.
[excited] Huge amounts of trust and
engagement! Associates understand that
their leaders are actually paying close
attention and are genuinely invested in
their professional growth. It
significantly reduces surprises.
And nobody wants to be surprised at their
annual evaluation.
[While Laughing] I know I don't. Ongoing
guidance makes accountability much easier
and paves the way for evaluations to be
clearer and fairer. And as Mr. Sam
pointed out, it reinforces strengths,
too. Early acknowledgment of success
encourages continued excellence and
really builds an associate's confidence.
Catch them doing something right, or help
them course-correct, and tell them
immediately! [thoughtful] That’s a
fantastic framework, Alex. Redirect the
drift, reinforce the success, and do it
in real-time.
Next time on Walmart Academy's The Art of
Feedback, we’ll dive into the actual
delivery and phrasing of these
conversations.