[Inhale] Welcome back to The Leadership
Loop. I’m Jamie, and as always, I’m
joined by my co-host and resident
leadership strategist, Alex.
[Smoothly] Great to be here, Jamie. Today
we’re diving into a topic that makes
pretty much everyone sweat a little bit:
feedback. Specifically, we're kicking
things off with the psychology and
perception behind it.
[chuckles] Yes, the dreaded "F-word" of
the corporate world. But before we get
into the "how-to" of delivering effective
feedback, we really need to understand
how it's actually processed by the person
sitting across from us, right?
[with confidence] Exactly. That’s step
one. And the biggest misconception we
have to bust right out of the gate is
this idea that feedback is a weapon or a
trophy. At its core, feedback is simply
information. It’s a data point. It is not
inherently good or bad.
Okay, rationally, [sighs] I hear you. But
let's be honest—when my manager says,
"Can I give you some feedback?" my heart
rate definitely spikes. Why doesn't it
feel like just data?
Because of what we call the "Personal
Lens." The meaning that you or I attach
to a piece of feedback is heavily shaped
by our personal mindset, our past
experiences, and the expectations we
walked into the room with.
So, we aren't just hearing the words;
we're filtering them through everything
that's ever happened to us in our
careers.
Exactly! [nods] Our brains are actually
wired for survival, which means they are
built to quickly interpret feedback
through this personal lens. We make these
lightning-fast, snap judgments about
whether this information is a threat
before we’ve even had a second to reflect
on the actual intent behind the message.
[thoughtful] That makes so much sense.
That psychological reality completely
explains why you can give the exact same
piece of feedback to two different people
and get two completely different
reactions.
Right! [emphatic] To Person A, that
feedback might feel incredibly
encouraging and immensely helpful. They
see it as a roadmap. But to Person
B—because of their specific lens—they
might experience those exact same words
as highly critical or discouraging.
So, as managers and even as peers, we
have to approach these conversations with
a heightened awareness. We aren't just
managing the work; we are navigating
another human being's psychological
wiring.
Beautifully said. [thoughtful] You know,
it always brings me back to that powerful
quote by Maya Angelou. She said, "I've
learned that people will forget what you
said, people will forget what you did,
but people will never forget how you made
them feel." If leaders can keep that at
the center of their feedback strategy, it
changes the entire dynamic.
Such a perfect note to wrap up this
segment on. [satisfied] Understanding the
personal lens is the absolute foundation.
Up next, we'll talk about how to actually
deliver that information once you
understand the psychology. [excited]
Stick around!